Guide to the W. M. Piatt and Company records, 1914-1973 RL.11770
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
W. M. Piatt and Company records
1914-1973
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Piatt, William M.
RL.11770
12 Linear Feet 8 boxes Approximately 6400 items
Collection comprises correspondence, blueprints, proposals relating to construction or the improvement of sewage and wastewater treatment systems. Includes substantial amounts of material on the sewage treatment system for Winston-Salem and Durham, North Carolina. Other North Carolina localities and clients documented in the collection are Burlington Mills, Claremont, Cooleemee, Cothran, Cramertown, Dallas, Erwin Mills, Fairbanks Morse Company, Mooresville, Mebane, North Wilkesboro, and Wake Forest.
Arrangement
Records are grouped by location.
Historical Note
Company founded in Durham, N.C., 1910, with the name Piatt and Davis, Engineers; primarily responsible for designing sewage and wastewater treatment systems and plants. The company designed the Durham Waterworks, constructed in 1917 on Hillandale Road; also designed the Lake Michie dam. One of their largest projects was the expansion of the Winston-Salem wastewater treatment system in the late 1950s. The firm's founder, William M. Piatt III, originally from Pennsylvania, owned the Lochmoor residence in Durham. His partner was a P.D. Davis.
The company had several names, starting with Piatt and Davis, Engineers, then Piatt and Davis and Associates; and by 1968, W. M. Piatt and Company. The company still exists, with headquarters in Garner, N.C.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The W.M. Piatt records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a deposit in 1984.
Scope and Contents
Collection comprises correspondence, blueprints, proposals, and reports relating to construction or the improvement of sewage and wastewater treatment systems in the North Carolina Piedmont. Includes substantial amounts of material on a major expansion of the sewage treatment system for Winston-Salem, Forsyth County, for which the firm was a consultant to the city and county, and multiple projects in Durham County, North Carolina.
Other North Carolina localities and clients documented in the collection are Burlington Mills, Claremont, Cooleemee, Cothran, Cramertown, Dallas, Erwin Mills, Fairbanks Morse Company, Mooresville, Mebane, North Wilkesboro, and Wake Forest. Most of the projects date from the latter half of the 20th century.
Engineering firms -- Durham (N.C.); Sewage disposal plants -- History -- North Carolina; Sewer design -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- Industry; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Blueprints
- Company records
  - Erwin Mills (Box 1)
  - Cramertown (Box 1)
  - Cooleemee (Box 1)
  - Fairbanks Morse Company (Box 1)
  - North Wilkesboro (Box 1)
  - Burlington Mills (Box 1)
  - Cothran (Box 1)
  - Dallas (Box 1)
  - Mooresville, 1948-1955 (Box 2)
  - Winston-Salem, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Forsyth County, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Winston-Salem, 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Forsyth County (Box 3)
  - Mebane (Box 3)
  - Mebane, 1938-1968 (Box 4)
  - Wake Forest, 1954-1964 (Box 4)
  - Claremont (Box 5)
  - Wake Forest, 1958-1960 (Box 5)
  - Winston-Salem sewage treatment plant proposal, plans, blueprints, subcontracts, 1950s-1960s (Box 6)
  - Winston-Salem sewage treatment plant, 1956-1958 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Subcontrators (Box 7)
  - Durham New Hope Creek, 1927-1928 (Box 7)
  - Durham New Hope Creek, 1927-1928 (Box 8)
  - Wake Forest, 1935-1936 (Box 8)
  - Greenville proposal, 1914 (Box 8)
  - Durham report, 1923 (Box 8)
  - Cooleemee report, 1930 (Box 8)
  - Mebane reports, 1946-1961 (Box 8)
  - North Wilkesboro reports, 1950-1951 (Box 8)
  - Wake Forest reports, 1958-1961 (Box 8)
  - Winston-Salem proposal and reports, 1953-1970 (Box 8)